Finding Aid for Donald R. Brown Papers, 1949-1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donald R. Brown Papers 1949-1996
Brown, Donald R., 1925-
0495 Aa 2
Donald R. Brown was a professor in the University of Michigan Department of Psychology (1964-1996) and director of the U-M Center for Research on Learning and Teaching (CRLT). He was also co-director from its inception of the Integrated Premedical-Medical Program, known as Inteflex. Professor Brown published many articles in the area of personality and student development; he also presented papers at many symposia and was a consultant on topics of learning and teaching. The collection includes files from his career at the University of Michigan.
8 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection (donor no. 8894 ) came from Donald R. Brown in 1999.
The collection is open to research.
Donald R. Brown was born on March 5, 1925, in Chatham, New York. He received his A.B. degree from Harvard University in 1948 after an interruption for military service during World War II. He served in the US Army, European Theater of Operations, 1943-1946, and was among the first American soldiers to arrive at the Dachau concentration camp. In 1951 he received his Ph.D. from the University of California at Berkeley. He began his teaching career at Bryn Mawr College, 1951-1964. While on the faculty here, Professor Brown collaborated with Nevitt Sanford on a famous longitudinal study of Vassar women.
In 1964 Professor Brown accepted a professorship in psychology at the University of Michigan under department chairman, Wilbert J. McKeachie (1961-1971). With a dual appointment he was both professor of psychology in the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts (LS & A) and research scientist in the Center for Research on Learning and Teaching (CRLT).
The student disruptions of the early 1960s inspired Brown to consider alternative educational models. He became involved in assessments of the Pilot Residence Hall Program and was a member of its Standing Committee. In the same vein, in 1967 Brown assisted Theodore Newcomb in establishing the Residential College. Brown and Newcomb conducted a longitudinal study on residential-academic units with a consortium of five universities. From 1964 onward he was a senior research scientist for the CRLT, and the director from 1983 to 1994. The CRLT was one of the first centers of its kind in the country, its dual role encompassing service to the faculty and research on the basic problems and conditions of instruction. Here Brown was instrumental in training teaching fellows (graduate student instructors), in faculty development, and in implementing numerous evaluations on the effectiveness of classroom instruction.
Brown co-directed Inteflex from 1972 to 1994. A joint venture between the Medical School and LS & A, Inteflex offered a combined program for selected premedical students, leading to a medical degree. The intent was to provide a well-constructed humanities program in conjunction with medical studies. Since inception all Inteflex classes, LS & A and standard Medical School classes have been followed in a study of value development and socialization into professional life. This study includes 2-year, 6-year, and 10-year post graduate follow-ups. Through the Inteflex program Brown was able to combine his intellectual interests in understanding the factors that shape students' educational experiences and outcomes with his social and political concerns about educational efforts.
Brown was involved in a variety of activities during his long career, including research fellowships and visiting scholar programs in Europe and Asia. He was a consultant in such areas as: psychology curriculum, designing and implementing curricular programs in psychology; and pre-medicine, liberal arts, and honors programs. Brown's research interests include: non-intellective factors in academic achievement, personality development and the education process, curriculum design and evaluation in higher education, cognitive measures of personality organization, and professional socialization of medical and law students. He published numerous articles in the area of student development in higher education, education in medicine, psychophysics of judgment and cognition, and women's life-span development. Since 1952 Brown and his colleagues carried out a longitudinal study of personality development on two cohorts of women graduates of Vassar College: women from classes of 1925 through 1936, and women from classes of 1957 and 1958.
Throughout his tenure at the University of Michigan, Brown served on many committees, task forces, and editorial boards. For the Department of Psychology he was chairman of the Graduate Program in Personality Theory and Assessment from 1972 to 1984. The Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs (SACUA) awarded Brown the Distinguished Faculty Governance Award in 1993.
Brown retired from active faculty status on June 30, 1996. He continues to teach occasionally, most recently offering a course entitled, "Why Grandpa Went to War" about World War II.
The Donald R. Brown papers, a combination of administrative records and professional papers, are divided into three principal series: Psychology, Center for Research on Learning and Teaching, and Inteflex. These series are preceded by some biographical information
Subjects:
Brown, Donald R., 1925-; Learning, Psychology of.; Premedical education.; University of Michigan. Center for Research on Learning and Teaching.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Psychology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Integrated Premedical-Medical Program.; University of Michigan. Residential College.
- Biography
  - Vita December 1993 (Box 1)
  - Related biographical information (Box 1)
- Psychology
  The Psychology series includes correspondence, papers and publications, course material, and records of professional involvement. Brown was active in the American Psychological Association, serving on the editorial board and executive board, Division Two, from 1968 to 1985. During that time he and his colleagues, successfully launched a new journal Teaching of Psychology (TOP). TOP was published by Division Two of the APA for teachers of Psychology at the undergraduate level. Brown was associate editor from 1974 to 1985. Correspondence outlining the preliminary discussions and development of TOP are included in the APA subseries, but there is only one copy of the actual publication.
  The general correspondence, course materials, symposia presentations, and various publication detail Brown's interest in personality in the educational environment and the psychology of learning and teaching.
  - American Psychological Association (APA)
    - Annual Conventions/Symposia
      - APA meeting, Cincinnati, "Social Changes and the College Student: A Symposium," 1959 (Box 1)
      - APA Symposium. papers for publication 1964 (Box 1)
      - APA, Division Two, Chicago 1965 (Box 1)
      - Hawaii, Division Two, Presidential address 1972 (Box 1)
      - Washington 1976 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1979-1992 (Box 1)
    - Division Two Newsletter
      - Editorial Committee 1971-1973 (Box 1)
      - Robert Daniel, transition editor 1972-1974 (Box 1)
      - "The Undergraduate Major: A Look at Alternative Strategies, Present and Future", May 1973 (Box 1)
    - Teaching of Psychology (TOP), 1974-1984
      - History of TOP (Box 1)
      - Correspondence 1973-1984, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence, B-Z 1976-1993, 20 folders (Box 1)
    - By topic 1976-1992
      - American Educational Research Association (Box 1)
      - Association of American Medical Colleges (Box 1)
      - Canadian Journal of Behavioral Science (Box 1)
      - Capara, Gian, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Choice (Box 2)
      - Contemporary Psychology (Box 2)
      - Journal of Personality and Social Psychology (Box 2)
  - Course materials
    - Background sources
      - Bryn Mawr articles, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Insight puzzles (Box 2)
    - Courses
      - Human Behavior, Residential College 1968-1969, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Psychology of the Unconscious 1950 (Box 2)
      - Psychology 101 1958 (Box 2)
      - Psychology 192 (Box 2)
      - Psychology 210 (Box 2)
      - Psychology 210, Computer Simulation (Box 2)
      - Psychology 519 (Box 2)
      - Psychology 653 (Box 2)
      - Psychology 682 (Box 2)
      - Psychology 753, 9 folders (Box 2)
      - Social Psychology 780 (Box 2)
    - Topical
      - Factor Analysis: Rationals and Basic Assumptions (Box 2)
      - Factors Influencing Students, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Life, Learning, and Locale, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Perceptual Consequences of Success and Failure (Box 2)
      - Psychoanalysis Finally Explained (Box 2)
      - Time Error papers, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Papers
    - "Can Social Psychology Make A Contribution to Legal Education?" 1971 (Box 2)
    - "Discussion of Perceptual Techniques in the Analysis of Personality," 1949 (Box 2)
    - "Effects of Individual Differences in Cognitive Style in Absolute Judgments of Physical and Social Stimuli" (Box 2)
    - "Emerging Social Problems" (Box 2)
    - "Growth and Development of Students in Experimental Programs" (Box 3)
    - "Instructional Centers, Curriculum Change, and Student Development" (Box 3)
    - "Integration and Separation of Cognitive Systems in Judgment: A Personality Topology" 1962 (Box 3)
    - "Longitudinal Program of Evaluation of Socialization and Achievement in Medical, Legal, and Liberal Arts Programs" (Box 3)
    - "Perceptual Consequences of Success and Failure" (Box 3)
    - "Personality Theory and AL Theory" (Box 3)
    - "Prediction of NBME Scores in an Accelerated Program" 1978 (Box 3)
    - "Preparation for College Teaching in a Research Dominated Reward System" (Box 3)
    - "Professional Development of Women Physicians: A Longitudinal Analysis" (Box 3)
    - "Student Activism as a Derivative of Developmental Stress" 1967 (Box 3)
  - Reprints and Publications
    - Abstract, British Psychological Society Student Change and Innovating Environments, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Book Reviews
      - Contemporary Psychology, 4 articles (Box 3)
      - The Rite of the Ph. D. 1962 (Box 3)
      - Subliminal Perception: The Nature of a Controversy, New Scientist 1972 (Box 3)
    - Adaptation-Level Theory Individual Differences and Adaptation-Level Theory, 1971 (Box 3)
    - American Journal of Psychology Stimulus-Similarity and the Anchoring of Subjective Scales, 1953 (Box 3)
    - American Philosophical Society, Year Book of 1954 Report of the Committee on Research (Box 3)
    - Educational and Psychological Measurement Personality Change as a Validation of the Breiter Differential-Change Scales, 1968 (Box 3)
    - Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology
      - Word Frequency and the Measurement of Value Areas 1954 (Box 3)
      - Authoritarianism, Verbal Ability, and Response Set 1959 (Box 3)
    - Journal of the American Medical Women's Association Students' Clinical Performance, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Journal of Educational Sociology Non-Intellective Qualities and the Perception of the Ideal Student by College Faculty, 1960 (Box 3)
    - Journal of Medical Education Actuarial Prediction of Performance In a Six-Year A.B.-M.D. Program, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Journal of the National Association of Women Deans and Counselors Value Change in College Women, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Journal of Personality Time-Error and the Separation of Cognitive Systems, 1966 (Box 3)
    - Journal of Personality and Social Psychology
      - Individual Perceptual Styles Following Induced Failure 1966 (Box 3)
      - Factors Influencing Value Change Among College Graduates in Adult Life 1974 (Box 3)
    - Journal of Social Issues
      - Some Educational Patterns, 1956 (Box 3)
      - Student Stress and the Institutional Environment 1967 (Box 3)
      - Encounters with Some Negro and White Freshmen With a Public Multiversity 1969 (Box 3)
      - Journal of Social Psychology College Environment, Personality, and Social Ideology of Three Ethnic Groups, 1956 (Box 3)
      - Perspectives Student Stress and Student Development, 1969 (Box 3)
      - Psychological Review Values, Word Frequencies, and Perception, 1953 (Box 3)
  - Residential College
    - General Background (Box 3)
    - Pilot Program (Box 3)
    - "Student Comments on the Core Curriculum" 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - Studies
      - 1967 "A Small Residential College Compared with Three Control Populations" (Box 3)
      - 1967 Self-Selection and Change, The Cluster College, Chapter 6 (Box 3)
      - 1968 "Freshmen Entering the Residential College: Comparison with Other LSA Freshmen" (Box 3)
      - 1969 "Student Development as a Function of Clark-Trow Type" (Box 3)
      - 1970 "Reactions of Residential College Faculty to the College, the Students, and the Core Curriculum" (Box 3)
      - 1971 "The University of Michigan's Residential College" (Box 3)
      - 1976 "What Happens When It's Over? Residential College Graduates, 1971-1974" (Box 3)
  - Symposia, in chronological order
    - Symposium on Mental Health in the Classroom: Experiences at the College Level, Bryn Mawr (Box 3)
    - The Role and Status of Women in Soviet Russia, Mary Winsor Symposium, Bryn Mawr 1964, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Urbanization and the College Student, Minneapolis, The Patterning of Students in Their Group Relationships 1966 (Box 3)
    - Second International Symposium on Educational Testing, Montreux 1975, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Kent State Sixth Annual Workshop in College Teaching 1975 (Box 3)
    - Improving University Teaching, International Conferences
      - Heidelberg 1976 (Box 3)
      - Aachen 1978 (Box 3)
      - Vancouver 1989 (Box 3)
    - XXIst International Congress of Psychology, Paris July, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Social Science Curriculum Faculty College, University of Wisconsin-Oshkosh 1977 (Box 3)
    - The Impact of College on Students, The Canadian Experience, Newfoundland 1977 (Box 3)
    - XIXth International Congress of Applied Psychology, Munich 1978 (Box 3)
    - Baldwin-Wallace College Fall Faculty Conference, Berea, Ohio 1978 (Box 4)
    - The Research on Aggression in Psychology, University of Rome 1979 (Box 4)
    - Pursuit of Excellence in Higher Education, Keimyung University, Daegu, Korea 1979, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - A Decade of Experience with Cost-Effective Models for Medical Education, University of Missouri-Kansas City 1981 (Box 4)
    - Advanced Study Institute, Advances in Measuring Cognition & Motivation, Athens, Greece 1984 (Box 4)
    - XXIV International Congress of Psychology, Sydney, Australia 1988 (Box 4)
    - Chinese Academy of Sciences, Lecture Tour 1988 (Box 4)
    - American Educational Research Association, AERA 1989 (Box 4)
    - Wakonse Conference on College Teaching 1990, 1992 (Box 4)
    - III European Congress of Psychology, Tampere, Finland 1993 (Box 4)
    - Seventh European Conference on Personality, Madrid 1994 (Box 4)
  - Topical
    - American Association for Higher Education, an interview 1991 (Box 4)
    - American Association for University Professors (AAUP) 1990-1991, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Ann Arbor Schools Testing Committee 1966 (Box 4)
    - Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics 1984-1987 (Box 4)
    - Festschrift
      - Jack Atkinson, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Wilbert McKeachie (Box 4)
    - Max Planck Institute for Human Development and Education, Fulbright Fellowship 1982-1983 (Box 4)
    - Wallenberg Committee (Box 4)
- Center for Research on Learning and Teaching 1964-1993
  The Center for Research on Learning and Teaching was established by the faculty as a resource for improving the quality of teaching at the university. Its areas of support include: consultation, project funding, workshops and colloquia, faculty orientation, teaching assistant training, course evaluation, computers and teaching, testing services, and instructional research and development. Brown served as CRLT director from 1983 to 1994, replacing Wilbert McKeachie. Both the Residential College and Inteflex were developed by the CRLT and Brown was instrumental in both institutions.
  - Administration 1983-1993
    - Deans/Presidents/Directors
      - Appointment letter 1983 (Box 4)
      - Connie Cook (Box 4)
      - James Duderstadt, President (Box 4)
      - Mary Ann Swain, Office of Academic Affairs (Box 4)
      - Linda Wilson, Office of Research 1987 (Box 4)
    - Executive Committee Minutes 1982-1993, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Faculty
      - Evaluation (Box 4)
      - Orientation (Box 4)
      - Workshops (Box 4)
    - IDQ/Evaluation & Examinations Office (Box 4)
    - Policy Committee 1982-1992 (Box 4)
    - Program Review (Box 4)
    - Senior Staff/McKeachie (Box 4)
    - Staff Meetings (Box 4)
  - Budget
    - 1992-1993 (Box 5)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 5)
  - Computer Activities, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, bound, outgoing only 1979-1990 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, two way
    - 1979-1988 (Box 6)
    - 1992-1994, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Faculty Development Fund 1992-1994 (Box 6)
  - Grants, chronological
    - Founders Endowment, S.C. Erickson (Box 6)
    - Presidential Initiatives Fund 1987 (Box 6)
    - Program Initiatives Grants 1987 (Box 6)
    - Undergraduate Initiatives Fund 1987 (Box 6)
    - Lilly Endowment
      - Background 1974-1981 (Box 6)
      - Correspondence 1983-1991 (Box 6)
      - Evaluation 1989-1990 (Box 6)
      - Fellows 1983-1986, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Post-Lilly Teaching Fellows Spring Retreat, First Annual 1993 (Box 6)
    - Post Doctoral Fellows Program 1986-1992, 8 folders (Box 6)
  - School of Engineering
    - "Next Generation Engineering Curriculum", NSF proposal 1990 (Box 7)
    - College of Engineering/CRLT Faculty Development Program 1991 (Box 7)
  - Topical
    - Motlow Community College presentation 1991 (Box 7)
    - National Center for Research to Improve Postsecondary Teaching (NCRIPTAL) grant 1986
      - Budget 1986 (Box 7)
      - Correspondence 1985-1989 (Box 7)
      - EDUCOM/NCRIPTAL Higher Education Software Awards 1987 (Box 7)
      - Research papers, Robert Kozma, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Robert Kozma 1990-1992, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Self-Help Lab, transfer of Michigan Media 1987-1989 (Box 7)
    - TA Training
      - Domestic 1983-1991, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - International 1985-1993, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Visitors
      - Domestic (Box 7)
      - Foreign 1971-1994, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Robert Young, visiting scholar 1985 (Box 7)
- Inteflex 1972-1994
  - Administration
    - Academic Review Board/Promotion 1973-1988
      - Memos 1973-1987, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Workshop 1986 (Box 7)
    - Admissions Committee
      - Background information 1973 (Box 7)
      - Memos 1973-1985 (Box 7)
      - Studies 1972-1982, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Faculty/Staff Meetings 1987-1988, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Nick Steneck, acting co-director 1982-1983 (Box 7)
    - Program Enrollment reduction 1984-1987 (Box 7)
  - Budget/Appointments 1972-1994 (Box 8)
  - Clippings/articles (Box 8)
  - Correspondence with medical colleges 1991 (Box 8)
  - Curriculum
    - Courses
      - Freshman Seminar, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Introduction to Patient Care, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Anatomy, 506/507 (Box 8)
      - Botany-Zoology 106 1975 (Box 8)
      - Calculus 115 (Box 8)
      - Chemistry (Box 8)
      - Ethics, Philosophy 644 (Box 8)
      - History (Box 8)
      - Microbiology, 420, 520, 521 (Box 8)
      - Psychology
        - 150 (Box 8)
        - 380 1977-1987 (Box 8)
        - 425 (Box 8)
    - Degree requirements 1973-1982 (Box 8)
    - Design
      - Correspondence 1972-1990, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Preliminary reports 1971-1972 (Box 8)
      - Program descriptions 1975 (Box 8)
      - Workshop/meeting 1986, 1987 (Box 8)
  - Evaluation
    - Attrition 1986, 1987 (Box 8)
    - Evaluation program 1975-1976 (Box 8)
    - Evaluation Advisory Committee 1978-1980, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - "Report of Evaluative Data Regarding the Inteflex Program," 1981 (Box 8)
    - Evaluative Reports by CRLT, inventory (Box 8)
    - Papers and Publications, bibliography (Box 8)
    - Topical reports on Inteflex Program, list (Box 8)
    - Report to Participants 1991, 1992 (Box 8)
    - Course Evaluation Summaries 1992, 1993 (Box 8)
  - Grants
    - Commonwealth Fund, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - "Coordinating the Humanities and Social Science Experience" 1987 (Box 8)
    - Other 1980-1983 (Box 8)